Guide to the George and Joan Violin Collection 1950, 1994, undated PR 338
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
George A. and Joan G. Violin collection
1950, 1994, undated
PR 338
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
2.0 Linear feet in one flat box
The collection includes the work of photographers Louis Faurer (1916-2001) and Arnold Newman (1918-2006) and artist Vincent D. Smith (1929-2003). Faurer is represented by four images from 1950s New York City; Newman by eight undated portraits; and Smith by a signed suite of prints of eight of his etchings from 1965-1966 concerning African-American life and racial animosity.
Violin, George A.
Violin, Joan G.
Arrangement Note
The collection is arranged by artist.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers by appointment only.
Immediate Source of Acquisition Note
Gift of George A. and Joan G. Violin, 2016 and 2017.
Scope and Contents Note
The collection includes the work of photographers Louis Faurer (1916-2001) and Arnold Newman (1918-2006) and artist Vincent D. Smith (1929-2003). Faurer is represented by four images from 1950s New York City; Newman by eight undated portraits; and Smith by a signed suite of prints of eight of his etchings from 1965-1966 concerning African-American life and racial animosity. Further details on the individual photographs and the suite of etchings are detailed below in the container list.
Faurer, Louis, 1916-2001; Newman, Arnold, 1918-2006; Smith, Vincent, 1929-; African Americans--Pictorial works; Celebrities; Etchings; Photographs; Portrait photography
- Louis Faurer Photographs, circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents Note
  Includes four gelatin silver prints of images taken in New York City. The container list includes titles and other details as recorded by the curator of N-YHS's Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections.
  - Untitled, NY, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Printed 1980; signed & titled on verso in graphite Louis Faurer; verso in graphite – lower left, circled “152”; verso lower center “PF109137”; verso lower right “20.17”; sheet: 10 7/8 x 13 7/8”; image: 8 x 11 1/4”.
  - San Genaro Festival, New York, NY, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Signed & titled on verso in graphite Louis Faurer; verso in graphite – lower left “284”; verso lower center “PF109269”; verso lower right “37.40”; sheet: 10 7/8 x 13 7/8”; image: 8 3/16 x 12 3/8”.
  - NY, NY, circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Printed 1981; signed & titled on verso in graphite Louis Faurer; verso in graphite – lower left “188”; verso lower center “PF109173”; verso lower right “24.34”; sheet: 10 7/8 x 13 7/8”; image: 6 9/16 x 9 7/8”.
  - Barnum & Baily Dressing Rooms, NYC, circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Printed 1981; signed & titled on verso in graphite Louis Faurer; verso in graphite – lower left “302”; verso lower center “PF109287”; verso lower right “39.37”; sheet: 10 7/8 x 13 7/8”; image: 8 1/16 x 12”.
- Arnold Newman Photographs, Undated
  Includes eight gelatin silver prints of portraits. The container list includes titles and other details as recorded by the curator of N-YHS's Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections.
  - Dorothy Norman, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Stamped on verso copyright Arnold Newman, 39 West 67th St., N.Y.C. 10023; lower center verso “PF82163” in graphite; “47” in graphite lower right verso; “6161” graphite center of verso; sheet: 13 /8 x 10 7/8”; image: 10 15/16 x 8 1/4”.
  - George Segal, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Stamped on verso copyright Arnold Newman, 39 West 67th St., N.Y.C. 10023; sheet: 10 7/8 x 13 7/8”; image: 8 1/16 x 13 9/16”; graphite verso lower center “PF 125671; graphite verso center “6274-2 17A”.
  - Robert Indiana, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Stamped on verso copyright Arnold Newman, 39 West 67th St., N.Y.C. 10023; sheet: 13 13/16 x 10 7/8”; image 12 ¼ x 9 9/16”; verso center graphite “5648A GAL; verso lower center graphite “PF84748”; verso lower right graphite “564B v1.001”.
  - Lily Harmon, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Stamped on verso copyright Arnold Newman, 39 West 67th St., N.Y.C. 10023; sheet 7 7/8 x 9 7/8” image: 6 7/16 x 9 3/8”; stamped on verso copyright Arnold Newman, 39 West 67th St., N.Y.C. 10023; verso center graphite “5341-1-20a”; verso lower left graphite “114”; verso lower center graphite “PF82230”.
  - Jimmy Ernst, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Stamped on verso copyright Arnold Newman, 39 West 67th St., N.Y.C. 10023; sheet: 9 7/8 x 7 7/8”; image: 9 ¾ x 6 7/16”; verso center graphite “550B”; verso lower center graphite “PF84768”; verso lower right graphite “550B v1.001”.
  - Carl Sandberg, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Stamped on verso copyright Arnold Newman, 39 West 67th St., N.Y.C. 10023; sheet: 13 3/4" x 10 15/16”; image: 9 15/16 x 7 ¾”; verso center graphite “lighter 2401”; verso upper right graphite “PD”; lower center graphite “PF125674”.
  - Helena Rubenstein, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Stamped on verso copyright Arnold Newman, 39 West 67th St., N.Y.C. 10023; sheet: 13 7/8 x 10 7/8”; image: 12 11/16 x 10 1/8”; verso center graphite “1340”; verso lower center graphite “PF 125673”; verso lower right graphite “V7 016”.
  - Joseph Stella (Box 1)
    Stamped on verso copyright Arnold Newman, 39 West 67th St., N.Y.C. 10023; sheet: 13 7/8 x 10 7/8”; image: 12 7/16 x 10”; verso top center graphite “#869”; verso lower center graphite “PF125652”; verso lower right graphite “V7 002”.
- Vincent D. Smith: Eight Etchings, 1965-1966, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Includes a cased suite of etchings printed on Arches paper in 1994 by Kelly Driscoll at the Printmaking Workshop under the supervision of Robert Blackburn and the artist. Suite is number 27/40. Pages signed by artist and noted AP. Published by G.W. Einstein Company, Inc. The etchings are titled "Dispossess," Shadows in Harlem," The Man in Harlem," "Mississippi Incident," "Down on the Farm," "First Day of School," "Housing Northern[?] Style," and "The Long Hot Summer."